in this video we're gonna focus on
centripetal acceleration and also how to
solve some physics problems associated
with it let's see if you have an object
moving to the right and it's speeding up
if it's speeding up and moving to the
right the acceleration is positive so
the acceleration and the velocity
vectors they're parallel to each other
now let's see if you have another object
that is still moving to the right but
instead of speeding up this object is
slowing down so if it's slowing down
that means the acceleration is negative
the acceleration and velocity vectors
are opposite to each other but what
happens if an object is moving at
constant speed in a circle what's
happening is there an acceleration in
the other examples if an object is
moving straight at constant speed there
is no acceleration now if it's moving at
constant speed in a circle there is
acceleration is not defined as the
change in speed over the change in time
rather acceleration is the change in
velocity divided by the change in time
and so even though this object is moving
at constant speed if the direction
changes the velocity changes because
velocity speed of direction and if the
velocity changes that means there's an
acceleration so this object experiences
an acceleration that points towards the
center of a circle which is known as
centripetal acceleration or center
secant acceleration now the centripetal
acceleration depends on the speed of the
object and also the radius of the circle
they'd always points towards a circle so
let's say if you have an object moving
to the right the centripetal
acceleration vector is perpendicular to
the velocity of the object
and is equal to V squared divided by R
where V is the speed and R is the radius
of the circle if you increase the speed
of an object while it's moving in a
circle the centripetal acceleration will
increase now if you double the speed by
what factor will the centripetal
acceleration increase by two squared is
four so if we double the speed decent
ripple acceleration will increase by a
factor four if you triple the speed the
acceleration will increase by a factor
of nine now what about the radius of the
circle what's the relationship between a
radius and the centripetal acceleration
if you increase the radius of the circle
the centripetal acceleration will
decrease these two are inversely related
so let's say if you double the value of
R what happens to the acceleration to
find out anything that doesn't change
plug in one if the speed doesn't change
replace over for one since our doubles
plug no tuned so the acceleration is
going to be half of its value if the
radius triples the acceleration is going
to be one-third of its value now what if
you make the circle smaller what if you
reduce the radius to half of its value
what happens 1 divided by 1/2 is 2 so if
you decrease the radius the centripetal
acceleration will increase if you cut it
in half is going to double if you
decrease it by a factor of 3 the
centripetal acceleration will triple now
here's a question for you what's gonna
happen if you reduce the radius to
one-fourth of its value and you increase
the speed by a factor of three what
effect will this have on a centripetal
acceleration to find out just plug it in
3 squared is 9 9 divided by 1/4 is the
same as
9 times 4 so this intrepid oaks
elevation will increase by a factor of
36 now there's some other stuff you need
to know how do you find the speed of the
object if it's moving in the circle at
constant speed by the way whenever an
object moves in a circle at constant
speed the object is moving with uniform
circular motion if the speed is not
constant it's a non uniform circular
motion now in order to find the
centripetal acceleration you need to be
able to determine the speed of the
object because the object is moving at
constant speed there's one equation that
we need to know D is equal to V T so V
is the distance traveled divided by the
time the distance traveled is basically
the distance around a circle and the
distance around a circle is known as the
circumference the circumference of a
circle is 2 pi times the radius of the
circular and because we're dealing with
periodic motion that's a motion that
repeats it goes on forever and ever you
can keep going on around a circle as
many times as you want you need to deal
with something known as the period the
period is the time it takes to complete
one full cycle and the period is known
as capital T lowercase T is simply the
time it takes to go from point A to
point B capital T is the time it takes
in making one revolution one cycle so
that's the period frequency is 1 divided
by the period so let's say if it takes
point 25 seconds to make one revolution
that would be the period the period is
0.25 seconds the frequency is one of
0.25 which is basically 4 so if it takes
only point 25 seconds to make one
evolution then you can do four
revolutions in one second and that's the
frequency the frequency is the number of
cycles that you can complete in one
second the period is the time it takes
to complete just one cycle now let's
work on some word problems a penny rests
45 centimeters from the center of a
spinning disk if the penny moves at a
constant speed of 2.5 meters per second
what is the acceleration the centripetal
acceleration rather acting on the penny
so all we need to do in this problem is
use this former the centripetal
acceleration is the square of the speed
divided by the radius of the circle now
we have the speed V is 2.5 meters per
second now what about the radius of the
circle now it rests 45 centimeters from
the center of the spinning disks so
that's the radius however it needs to
convert that to meters so how can we
convert centimeters to meters it's
important to know that one meter is
equal to 100 centimeters so all you got
to do is divide it by 100 so 45
centimeters is 0.45 meters so the
centripetal acceleration is going to be
2.5 meters per second squared divided by
the radius of 0.45 meters
so the acceleration is 13.9 running to
nurse ten meters per second squared
and so that's all you need to do in this
problem number two a ball travels around
a horizontal circle of radius 1.5 meters
and makes three revolutions every second
what is the frequency of the ball the
frequency okay that doesn't look like a
F the frequency is the number of cycles
divided by the time so it's the number
of cycles that occur in one second so we
have three revolutions or three cycles
that occurs in one second so the
frequency is just three it's three
revolutions per second now what about B
what is the period the period is the
time divided by the number of cycles so
one second in one second there are three
revolutions where this ball travels
three Aleutians in one second so the
period is one over three you can also
find it using this T is 1 over F so if F
is 3 then T is 1/3 so the period is 1/3
second per revolution
now what about Part C what is the linear
speed to find a linear speed it's going
to be 2 pi R the distance around a
circle divided by the period the time it
takes to making one revolution around a
circle so in this problem we can see
that the radius is 1.5 meters and we
know the period is 1/3 of a second so
it's 2 pi times 1.5 which is 3 PI
/ third so this is equal to nine pi
which as the decimal that's twenty eight
point two seven meters per second so
that's the linear speed so now Part D
what is this interpreter acceleration
the acceleration is V squared divided by
R so it's going to be twenty eight point
two seven squared divided by the radius
which is one point five and so relative
nearest whole number it's about five
hundred and thirty three meters per
second squared so that's the centripetal
acceleration now sometimes you can
combine these two equations if you want
to so we have this equation and we know
V is two PI R over T so I'm going to
replace V with two PI R of T but first
I'm going to rewrite it I'm gonna be
write this as one over R times V squared
and V squared that's going to be two PI
R over T squared 2 squared is 4 so we
get four PI squared times R squared
divided by T squared and so you can
cancel an R so in terms of the radius
and a period the centripetal
acceleration is going to be 4 PI squared
R divided by T squared so whenever you
encounter a problem that gives you the
radius of the circle and the time it
takes to complete one revolution you can
use this equation to find the
centripetal acceleration directly
without having to find the linear speed
first unless you have to find out then
you can use that
let's move on to number three the Earth
orbits the Sun at a distance of 150
times 10 to the 6 kilometers
what is this interpretative acceleration
of the earth around the Sun so let's
draw a picture so let's say this is the
Sun let's say that's the earth now we're
going to assume that the Earth orbits
the Sun in a nearly circular orbit so
what is this interpretative acceleration
that's acting on the earth around the
Sun how can we find it so we have the
orbital radius the distance between
anywhere on this orbit and the earth and
that's equal to 150 times 10 to the 6
kilometers so that's R however we need
to convert kilometers to meters and it
turns out that one kilometer is a
thousand meters so 150 times 10 to the 6
times a thousand is one point five times
ten 11 meters so that's the radius now
what other information do we need in
order to find this insurable
acceleration now recall the last
equation that we used that we came up
with earlier we said the in central
acceleration is 4pi squared times R
divided by T squared so we have R we
don't have the linear speed of the earth
but do we know the period how long does
it take the earth to orbit the Sun it
takes the earth one year to make a full
trip around the Sun so the period of the
earth is one here but we need that in
seconds so let's convert one year into
seconds now we know that there's 365
days in a single year
so the unit years cancel and in one day
there's 24 hours and within a single
hour there are 60 minutes and each
minute is equivalent to 60 seconds so
365 times 24 times 60 times 60 so the
period of the earth in seconds around
the Sun is 31 million 536,000 seconds so
now we have everything that we need to
get the answer
now let's plug in everything so it's
gonna be four pi squared times the
radius which is 1.5 times 10 to the 11
divided by the period which is this big
number but don't forget to square
so the centripetal acceleration of the
earth around the Sun is 5.95 times ten
to the minus three meters per second
squared so that's the answer now let's
move on to our last problem number four
a jet moving east at 400 meters per
second makes a circular turn to head
north in an arc of radius of 4
kilometers what is the acceleration of
the jet so let's draw a picture
so let's say this is the jet and it's
moving east and then eventually it's
going to make a circular turn to head
north now the turn is probably gonna
have to be much much wider in a turn so
right now this is a portion of a circle
notice that you can extend a circle if
you want to so that arc has a circular
radius and that radius is 4 kilometers
so the fact that it's turning from east
to norv means that it's going to
experience a centripetal acceleration
during that turn our goal is to find
acceleration at that point and we have
what we need we have the velocity or
rather the speed and we have the radius
when you combine the speed with the
direction then that becomes the velocity
so all we need to do is just use the
formula AC is equal to V squared over R
so V is 400 and R we need to convert
kilometers to meters now if we one
kilometer is a thousand meters for
kilometers is 4,000 meters so we have
400 times another 400 divided by 4000
where 4000 is 400 times 10 so we can
cancel a 400 and we can cancel a zero so
it's 40 over 1 which is 40 so this
intrepid acceleration is 40 meters per
second squared so that's the answer to
Part A now let's move on to Part B how
many earth Gees is this G is the
gravitational acceleration and on earth
it's 9.8 meters per second squared so we
need to convert meters per second
squared to G's so we have a centripetal
acceleration of 40 meters per second
squared and one g is equal to nine point
eight meters per second
squared so we could cancel these units
and we can get the number of G's so it's
40 divided by 9.0 and so this
acceleration is about four point zero
eight of G's so I'm just going to put G
so the centripetal acceleration that
this jet is experiencing it's basically
a little bit more than four times or IFS
gravity so that's what it means
so if you have something that is
experiencing 10 G's then imagine
experiencing a weight force that's ten
times greater than your weight you can
feel very heavy and so ten G's is a lot
you experience an acceleration that's
ten times the gravitational acceleration
of the earth